we can represent three finite sets a b
and c by the Venn diagram shown here now
suppose we want to find the cardinality
or the number of elements in the union a
union B Union C to do this we start by
taking the number of elements in a and
adding that to the number of elements in
B and adding that to the number of
elements in C unfortunately this is too
much because we've over counted the
elements in A and B so we remove the
cardinality of a intersect B
likewise we need to remove the
cardinality of a intersect C since we've
counted those elements twice and we need
to subtract the cardinality of B
intersect C since we've counted those
elements twice but now notice that the
elements that are in the intersection of
all three sets have been added three
times and subtracted three times so we
need to re-add the cardinality of a
intersect B intersect C this formula is
known as the three set inclusion
exclusion formula